Guide to the Philip Foner Papers TAM 153
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Philip Foner Papers
1870-1990
1960-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
TAM 153
20 Linear Feet in 19 record cartons and two drawers
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by the Foner family in 1995; additional materials were donated by Julian and Mildred Chazin in 1999, transferred from Lincoln University in 2006, and donated by Laura Foner in 2014. Accession numbers related to these gifts are 2001.001, 2001.006, and 2014.101.
Appraisal
In 2006, the library received an accretion of material for this collection from Lincoln University. Among these records, library staff identified a discrete grouping of approximately 1.5 linear feet of original correspondence and other documents relating to and created by Samuel Gompers. These records were clearly of different provenance than the majority of records in the collection created by or related to Philip Foner.
Wisconsin Historical Society holds the records of the American Federation of Labor during the years that Gompers served as its President, including a significant body of correspondence and other records he created in that role. In 2007, the library transferred the Gompers records to Wisconsin Historical Society, so that they would be in the same repository as the other main body of Gompers records held in a public archive.
Historical/Biographical Note
Philip Foner, a prominent and prolific historian of the American labor movement, was born in 1910. Radicalized by the Great Depression, he has been politically close to the Communist Party, and taught courses at several of its schools for workers. While he is best known for his multi-volume History of the Labor Movement in the United States, Foner is the author and editor of dozens of books, pamphlets and articles. For many years, Foner taught at Lincoln College, in Pennsylvania.
Custodial History
The Philip Foner Papers came to the library in several accretions over time. The first donation of 5 linear feet of papers came in 1995, shortly after Foner's death in 1994, and was transferred directly from his home. In 1999, Julian and Mildred Chazin donated their correspondence with Foner, which was added to the collection. An additional accretion of 12 linear feet was transferred from Lincoln University in 2006. The accession number associated with this gift is 2001.006. In 2014, Laura Foner donated a small amount of correspondence, which was also added to the collection. The accession number associated with this gift in 2014.101.
Audiocassette tapes 1-24 came to Tamiment Library from Haverford College. Tapes 25-28 were donated to the library by Marvin E. Gettleman in 2008.
Scope and Content Note
This unprocessed collection contains personal and professional correspondence, postcards, flyers, clippings, recordings of lectures, and memorabilia. Topics documented are Foner's relations with family, universities and other employers, the publication of his various works, and his far-flung travels and teaching positions throughout the former socialist bloc and in several developing countries.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Materials
Samuel Gompers papers were separated from this collection and transferred to the State Historical Society of Wisconsin in October 2007; a plaque was separated from this collection and returned to the Foner family in 2014.
Labor unions -- United States -- History; Communists -- United States.; Correspondence.; Working class |z United States |x History; Labor movement -- United States -- History; Clippings (information artifacts); Memorabilia.; Postcards.; Fliers (printed matter); Lincoln University (Pa.); Foner, Philip Sheldon, 1910-1994; Vandepaer, Elizabeth Foner; Foner, Laura; Chazin, Julian
- Framed photograph of Philip Foner recieving an award in Cuba, with Rhoda Lichtash, undated (Box 1)
- Mexico Before the World by P.E. Calles (Box 1)
- Working manuscript of The Iran-Contra Humor Book, circa 1985 (Box 1)
- Research files re: African Americans' involvement in civil and labor rights struggles and in the Communist Party USA, circa 1930-1980 (Box 1)
- Correspondence regarding Foner's Cuba and China trips (Box 1)
- Photographs from Cuba trip (Box 1)
- Labor Education Award plaque from the New York Labor History Association (Box 2)
- Publicity and other materials from Labor Research Association's luncheon honoring Foner (Box 2)
- Correspondence re: Foner's research, travels, publications, and other professional activities (Box 2)
- Research files re: Japanese trade unions (Box 2)
- Publishers' contracts (Box 2)
- Annotated typescript of History of the Labor Movement in the United States (and possibly History of Black Americans) (Box 3)
- Research files re: Communist Party USA, history of socialism, early U.S. labor unions, and women in the labor movement (Box 3)
- Correspondence re: Foner's travels (especially to China), research, publications, and other professional activities (Box 3)
- Foner's testimony before Subcommittee on Labor Standards (Box 3)
- Biographical materials (Box 3)
- Family photographs, 1940s, undated (Box 3)
- Research files regarding Philadelphia stevedore strike and academic freedom for Communists and African Americans, circa 1920-1950 (Box 4)
- Reviews of Foner's books, circa 1960-1995 (Box 4)
- Foner's articles on anti-Communism in U.S. labor history, African American labor history, racism, and the Cuban Revolution (Box 4)
- Annotated typescript of Paul Robeson Speaks (Box 4)
- Publicity and other materials from Foner's classes and lectures (Box 4)
- Biographical materials (Box 4)
- Foner's writings on 1946 Rochester strike, civil rights struggles for African Americans in Philadelphia, Tampa cigarworkers strikes, and other topics (Box 5)
- NYC Board of Higher Education report regarding charges against Foner at City College (Box 5)
- Research files regarding Upton Sinclair, U.S. labor history, and anti-slavery societies (Box 5)
- Biographical Materials (Box 5)
- Correspondence re: Foner's publications (Box 5)
- Correspondence re: Foner's research, publications, and personal and professional activities (Box 6)
- Publicity materials for lectures (Box 6)
- Minutes, memoranda, and news clippings re: Lincoln University faculty bargaining, undated (Box 6)
- Research files re: Samuel Gompers and Frederick Douglass, undated (Box 6)
- Correspondence re: Foner's research, publications, and other professional activities, undated (Box 7)
- Research files regarding Cuba, undated (Box 7)
- Promotional materials for Contemporary Films, Inc., undated (Box 7)
- Correspondence regarding Foner teaching at Lincoln University and his research, publications, and other professional activities, circa 1960-1980 (Box 8)
- ; Foner's syllabi and other materials for classes, circa 1960-1980 (Box 8)
- Research files re: Frederick and Helen Pitts Douglass, Samuel Gompers, and African Americans and race relations during the Civil War, Reconstruction, and early 20th century, undated (Box 9)
- Draft of lecture on American history delivered by Foner at the School for Democracy, undated (Box 9)
- Terence V. Powderly correspondence (originals), undated (Box 9)
- Research files regarding Socialist Party USA, U.S. labor history, and Frederick Douglass, 1870s-1880s, 1960s (Box 10)
- Research files regarding colonial/early U.S. history, Frederick Douglass, and African American labor history, undated (Box 11)
- Annotated typescript of IWW Free Speech Fights as Told by Participants, undated (Box 11)
- Research files re: Cuba, colonial and early U.S. history, slavery in the U.S., Frederick Douglass, African Americans and socialism, and U.S. labor history, undated (Box 12)
- Correspondence regarding Foner's research, publications, and other professional activities, circa 1970-1980 (Box 12)
- Research files regarding Samuel Gompers, undated (Box 12a)
- Research files regarding Samuel Gompers, undated (Box 12b)
- Newspaper clippings regarding African Americans and civil rights, circa 1960-1980 (Box 13)
- Handwritten notes for History of Black Americans, circa 1960-1980 (Box 13)
- Annotated typescript of History of Black Americans, 1974 (Box 14)
- Annotated typescripts of History of the Labor Movement in the United States, Frederick Douglass on Women's Rights, The Autobiographies of the Haymarket Martyrs, and other works, circa 1960-1980 (Box 15)
- Annotated typescripts of The Voice of Black America, British Labor and the American Civil War, and other works, circa 1970-1990 (Box 16)
- Annotated typescripts of History of the Labor Movement in the United States, The Voice of Black America, A History of Cuba and its Relations with the United States, When Karl Marx Died: Comments in 1883, and other works, circa 1960-1980 (Box 17)
- Lectures delivered at Haverford College from Sept. 9 through Dec. 9, 1982 by Philip Foner, for the course History of the American labor movement. (Cassette 1-24)
- Philip Foner's talks on the U.S. Centennial of 1976, at Brooklyn Polytechnic University (Cassette 25-28)
- Unprocessed materials (Box 18)